Hi and welcome back to another episode
with ItsDrDan and this time we're
going to be looking into gas laws.
So last time on our previous video
of introduction to gases and kinetic
molecular theory we learned that we
have little gas or little particles that
are bouncing all over the place moving
in constant speed motion and they're
applying pressures with inside of whatever
space they are located in they fill
whatever volume they are currently in.
So for example the air in your room,
it's in every square inch of your room.
It's not just in one little
location around our mouth.
It is everywhere then that's because all
those millions and millions of atoms that
are all around are all bouncing around
and moving and flowing, so There are
a lot of very simple laws, being that
these are ideal gases, talking about very
minimal interactions between each other.
We can describe them with laws,
meaning that we can use a lot of
mathematics to describe how can we
predict how they're going to function.
So, one of the first ones is Boyle's Law.
So, what Boyle's Law tells us is that
there is, whenever you have a pressure
and a volume of a gas, that are initial.
So whenever we have something that's
considered to be initial, we're
going to be representing that with,
so if I have an initial pressure,
that's going to be with a one.
If it's an initial
volume, that would be V1.
So whenever you have those two values,
they are going to be equal to a
final pressure and a final volume.
of that gas, meaning that let's say if I
took a, a balloon and I'm holding it in
my hand, well, what were to happen if you
were to try to compress it in your hand?
Is it going to resist you
or is it going to pop?
Well, if while you're pressing on
that balloon, you're going to feel it
resisting you until eventually it pops,
but for the longest time it will resist.
That's pressure.
So the whole idea that is, okay, is that
there's this inverse relationship here,
meaning that as you increase pressure,
the volume of which that gas is occupying
is going to decrease as a result.
So we can make a lot of predictions here.
So as pressure increases, going from
P1 to P2, volume is going to decrease.
If you go from P, uh, P1 to P2, so
initial to final, and it's decreasing.
The volume is going to be
increasing as a result.
So what does that look
like in terms of graphing?
Well, if you have, let's say, looking
at this, if we have our initial pressure
at initial volume, and let's say I
decrease the pressure and I go down,
so if I'm going downwards, well, as
that goes down, well, what's happening
is, well, the volume It's going to be
decreasing, it's going to be increasing.
So volume goes up as pressure goes down.
So it's all about that
inverse relationship.
So how can we, what exactly are you
going to have to solve mathematically?
Well, it's generally
pretty easy questions.
So if I have the following one and
I ask you this question here and
I say that we have a sample of gas
and it's placed inside of a piston.
Well, it...
A piston essentially
is this metal cylinder.
It's going to be pushing down.
It's going to be compressing
all the gases like I have here.
So if I have a little, a little piston
here, I have a gas inside of here.
They're bouncing all around
and this occupies 425
milliliters at one atmosphere.
So let's try to highlight all
that important information.
So we have 525 milliliters.
And that's at one atmosphere.
So, whenever you're reading these, what
we want to do is we want to write down
all of our given pieces of information.
So we have 425 milliliters.
and that's at one atmosphere.
So that tells you your V1 and
then your P1 of those two values.
Now it mentions that the
gas piston is compressed.
So you can see that, okay, it's
coming really close together.
So it's like the example I
said, if I push on a balloon,
what's going to be happening?
So when that compresses, it says
that the pressure reaches 3.
28 atmospheres.
So that means that as this pressure
is changing, it goes from 3.
28 atmospheres.
So what you see is that
pressure is increasing.
So, how can we try to
predict this problem?
Well, going back up, well as
pressure increases, so looking at
these, right, so pressure increases.
Volume should decrease.
So it's telling you that your final
answer should be a tinier volume.
It's a check for yourself.
Which makes it really nicer when
you're doing these problems.
We like predictable problems.
We don't want something that,
you know, it goes into something
that doesn't fit anywhere.
So we're trying to figure out V2.
So what we're going to be doing
initially is setting up our formula.
Meaning that I have P1
V1 is equal to P2 V2.
So we are trying to solve for V2 here.
So V2 is our unknown variable.
So the whole idea here is
we need to get it by itself.
Well, what's the easiest way to do that?
Well, if I divide both sides by
P2, what that's going to cause
is for the P2 values to cancel.
And that will, in a sense, get
V1 by itself, so we have P1,
P1 times V1, divided by P2, and
that's going to be equal to V2.
So, all we now need to do is
plug in all of our information.
Now, when you're plugging these
things in, whatever the common,
Variable is so in this case pressure.
They need to be in the same units.
They need to be able to cancel each other
out So when we are doing this, right
our initial pressure was one atmosphere
and that's going to be multiplied by
425 milliliters And that's all going to
be divided by pressure 2, which is 3.
28 atmospheres.
Alright, so when we do that, what
that's going to be all equal to is
that V2 will be equal to, um, 129.
6 mL.
Now, is that the correct sig figs?
We're just going to round it.
And you might notice there's three
sig figs for all of your givens.
So this will round to 130.
Milliliters.
Okay, and now this would be your final.
Your final answer there.
So that's how we do Boyle's Law.
For the next one, Charles Law.
Charles Law is another type of
really, another really common gas law.
So what this is telling you is that volume
is directly proportional to temperature.
And this could kind of make some sense
if you think back to the simulation that
I showed in my previous problem where
as we increase temperature, particles
start to move at a very rapid pace.
So when that happens, those
particles are going to be pushing
and banging against all the walls
of whatever its container is.
So if it's something that's flexible,
well, it's going to grow as a
result, so they're proportional.
So meaning that if, as initial volume,
if that's going to be increasing,
then You're going to see the same,
a proportional change in your
final temperature and final volume.
So the way that we can look at this
is a very different graphical picture,
is that if I have volume at an initial
temperature, and if I increase the volume,
Temperature is going to increase too.
They're both going to increase.
So if temperature increases,
volume should increase too.
They are directly proportional.
Now, one of the things about this
is, being that we're talking about
temperature, this is one of the units
that needs to be in the correct scale.
It needs to be in Kelvin.
Now, the reason behind that is because
Kelvin is an absolute unit scale.
Meaning that it only
refers to positive values.
You cannot do the mathematics here with
negatives or with zero as a possibility.
It has to be a positive number.
So anywhere from 0.
0001 all the way up to infinity, right?
So it's always a positive value.
So, now this is also predictable.
As volume increases,
temperature should increase.
If volume decreases...
Temperature should decrease.
So we should be able to predict our answer
too, which is always a nice thing to have.
We want as predictable as possible.
So the idea for this one, if
I had the following question,
so if I say I have a 2.
75 liter sample, okay, so we
have a volume, and it's at a
temperature of 25 degrees C.
When the amount of gas and pressure
are held constant, so being that that's
telling you that it's not relevant to
this problem It's helping you be able
to decide which formula to use this
time We know it's Charles law, but most
problems are given you have to pick
from all of them What is the new volume
when argon is heated to 45 degrees C?
So argon is being heated this Volume of
gas is going to be growing because they're
moving more rapidly so Now keep note, we
do have to convert all these to Kelvin.
So we have to use our
little Kelvin equation.
So why don't we write down
all these values we had.
So we had that volume 1 was 2.
75 liters.
We have, we don't have a
volume 2, kind of going through
these, so we have no volume 2.
That's a question mark.
And T1 and T2 were 25
degrees C and 45 degrees C.
Alright, so when you're going through
these, the first thing we have to do
is convert our temperatures to Kelvin.
So in order to do that, we
just take our temperatures.
So if I have T1, Kelvin is
just going to be that 25.
0 degrees C plus 273.
And what that's going to give
us, our first value is 298.
Kelvin for T1, and then T2, doing the
same mathematics, you're going to see
that that one's going to be 318 Kelvin.
All right, so now we can
plug it into our equation.
Our equation before was V1,
T1, is equal to V2 over T2.
So, what we're going to do is we're going
to rearrange it to get V2 by itself.
So what we can simply do is, being
that we want to get this by itself,
we can multiply both sides by T2.
This is going to cause the number of the
T2s on the right hand side to cancel,
giving us a new formula, or a rearranged
formula, of this is equal to V2.
And what we're simply going to be
doing is plugging in our variables.
So we have T2, which
was equal to 318 Kelvin.
We have V1, which was 2.
75 liters.
And then we have T1, which was 298 Kelvin.
Now, notice how the Kelvin ends
up canceling each other out,
leaving us only with a volume.
So when we go through this calculation,
what we're going to end up getting is 2.
93 liters of gas.
Now, does that make sense
based on what we saw?
Well, as you notice, temperature was
increasing as we went from T1 to T2.
So, if that's the case, volume should
also increase, and based on our original
volume, you can see that increase by a
little tiny bit when it was heated up.
So this gives you an idea of what we
are looking for with this gas law.
So as volume increases,
temperature should also increase.
Same thing with vice versa.
Temperature decreases,
volume should decrease.
The next law, so there's a lot of these,
but we'll go through them step by step.
This one is Gay Lussac's Law.
This one's also a very similar idea.
This one tells you that as pressure.
is directly proportional to temperature.
So if you think of your car tires,
for example, throughout the summer, as
it gets really hot out, the pressure
of your tires is going to increase.
This is one of the reasons why your
tires have a maximum recommended
pressure on your tires, because
if you overfill them, and then it
gets hot out, they will explode.
Versus when it gets to winter time and
you might have that air pressure light
that comes on saying low pressure.
Well, that's because all those
molecules are getting really cold
and they're starting to kind of
try to bundle up really closely.
So whenever you have a gas at initial
pressure and initial temperature,
this is proportional to the final
pressure and final temperature.
So it's a very similar graph
to the one I just showed you.
Instead though, when we have an initial
pressure and temperature and if I decide
to increase Pressure, temperature is going
to increase as well and it's the whole
idea that fast moving molecule picture the
faster They're moving if you have a solid
container that can't expand Let's say for
example, maybe a gas cylinder the steel
walls Well, if those molecules are heated
up, they're going to be really pushing
against those walls of that container So
once again, this is a direct relationship
meaning that They go together.
As pressure increases,
temperature increases.
They both increase together.
Or, the opposite is they
both decrease together.
Pressure goes down,
temperature comes down too.
So, what kind of problems would you have?
So, let's say if I gave
you the following one.
Let's say I had a balloon and I
decided to dump liquid nitrogen on it.
So, if you have a balloon and it's
at 3 atmospheres of gas, and it's
at room temperature, so about 300
Kelvin, and it's cooled down with
liquid nitrogen to a pressure of 0.
77 atmospheres.
What is the new
temperature of the balloon?
So if this thing is completely deflated,
and that's because those molecules
are so cold, they're moving really
slowly, they're not able to push
against the walls of the container
because they're not moving as fast.
So, same as before, we're going to
write down all of the key things.
So the first one is that the pressure
was at 3 atmospheres, and that was at a
temperature of 300 K, and notice how I
put the decimal place there to 3 sig figs.
Now, I mentioned that the pressure
changes to P2, and that's at 0.
77 atmospheres.
So T2 is not known, so we're going
to be using Our equation, which
was P1 over T1, is equal to P2, T2.
Okay, so we want to get T2 by itself.
Notice how T2 here is in the denominator,
so it's really not an easy thing.
to get by itself.
You have to multiply it and kind
of move a bunch of things around.
One thing about these equations, if
your variable is in the denominator,
or the part I have highlighted
in purple, what you can do is
you can use the inverse of this.
So if you have an inverse,
what that's doing is, is it's
flipping your whole equation.
So if we flip it, well, what's that
going to be doing if you flip something?
Well, You're just flipping it to be T1
P1 is equal to P2, or sorry, T2 over P2.
So if we do that, notice now
that T2 is now on the top.
Meaning that this makes it a little bit
easier to cancel out P2 in this case.
So now when we try to cancel things,
P2 and P2 cancel and it gets T2 by
itself in a really quick matter.
It's a good little trick to have
in your chemist's toolbox to store
for later as a mathematical tip.
So our formula in this case will
be P2 So taking what's over here,
P2 T1 over P1 is equal to T2.
So when we take all of our
numbers from earlier, we'll plug
in our new atmospheric pressure.
We'll plug in our original
temperature, so it would be 0.
77 atmospheres times 300 Kelvin.
And that's divided by three atmospheres.
So, when that happens, when we go through
that process, uh, what we're going to
be getting in a sense is, um, that the
temperature of our gas is going to be 77
Kelvin from our mathematics here, which
is the temperature of liquid nitrogen
when it is, uh, Portal on something.
So 77 Kelvin.
That is extremely cold.
So that is like roughly about negative
200 degrees Celsius to about or so.
It is extremely cold in terms of You
know the most freezing temperature
and then even beyond that The
next law is the Combined Gas Law.
The Combined Gas Law takes the previous
three and puts them all together.
So what exactly does that refer to?
Well, whenever we have the Combined
Gas Law, this is something that it
takes Boyle's Law, Charles Law, and Gay
Lussac's Law and puts them all together.
So this is something that, um, we're
going to go into on the subsequent video
of this to go into how all three of these
previous laws combine together to make one
unique law regarding change of a molecule.
So the past three, all the ones that
we're talking about are all about change.
Something is increasing,
something is decreasing.
Combined Gay Lussac's Law is
going to go into that too.
So...
Watch the next video, so that way it
breaks up the content for you, so you're
not getting a fire hose of information.
And I hope that to see you again
in the next video, to be able to
practice more of these gas laws.
And we'll go into combined, Avogadro's,
and then another video will be on
ideal gas law, going into that one.
Okay?
Look forward to seeing
you all in the future.
Alright, bye.